Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's daf דף daf is נ"ג,
Nun Gimmel, but we pick up
on נ"ב עמוד ב' Nun Beit Amud Beit from what I understand
we left off with
שאל תלמיד אחד shaal talmid echad at the asterisk about 20 lines
down left word on the line. The issue had just been that
the mishna משנה mishna had said that these various collars קולרים kolarim
you can be טובל tovel with it without taking it off of
the neck of the animal. You don't have to actually totally immerse
the animal, but at least the head of the animal, I assume
that's the case where that's more convenient than taking the collar off.
Anyway, the Gemara's גמרא Gemara issue was two things, number one, how
is the collar tamei טמא, tamei, isn't it something used for an
animal, not used for a person? To which the Gemara גמרא Gemara
had two answers, one is that it originally had been a person's
necklace
and therefore it retained its status of a vessel כלי kli and
the other had been that it is considered used by human because
a human uses it to control his animal. And then the question
is why being around the neck of the animal not a chatzitza
חציצה, chatzitza, to which the Gemara גמרא Gemara had two answers, either
that it was widened so it's loose or it's a type of
a chain that has a lot of holes and therefore it was
not a chatzitza חציצה. chatzitza. So now the Gemara גמרא Gemara in
the middle of these discussions about the issues of tumah טומאה tumah
of vessels כלים kelim and also about carrying on Shabbat שבת Shabbat
or having it on your animal on Shabbat שבת Shabbat tells us
two stories. שאל תלמיד אחד מגליל העליון את רבי אליעזר, Shaal talmid
echad migalil ha'elyon et Rabbi Eliezer, so one student from the Upper
Galilee asked Rabbi Eliezer, שמעתי שחולקין בין טבעת לטבעת, shemati shecholkinn beyn
tabaat l'tabaat, I heard that there's a distinction between different types of
rings. אמר לו שמא לא שמעת אלא לענין שבת, amar lo shema
lo shamata ela l'inyan Shabbat, maybe you only heard this regarding Shabbat
שבת, Shabbat, by Shabbat שבת Shabbat as we'll find out in the
next perek פרק, perek, if you have a ring that has a
seal you can't wear it on Shabbat שבת, Shabbat, if you have
a ring without a seal on it, a signet ring or a
non-signet ring, then you can wear it on Shabbat שבת, Shabbat, so
yes there's a difference regarding Shabbat שבת, Shabbat, that's where there's a
difference. דלענין טומאה דבר אחד היא, d'leinyan tumah davar echad hi, because
when it comes to laws of tumah טומאה tumah and tahorah טהרה,
tahorah,
דלענין טומאה דבר
אחד היא, d'leinyan tumah davar echad hi, it's all the same halacha
הלכה. halacha. So now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, דלענין טומאה דבר
אחד היא, d'leinyan tumah davar echad hi, is it really true for
tumah טומאה tumah all rings are the same? והתנן, vehatnan, we taught
in the mishna משנה mishna which we quoted yesterday, טבעת אדם טמאה,
tabaat adam t'mea, a ring for a person is tamei טמא tamei
because it's a vessel כלי, kli, וטבעת בהמה וכלים, v'tabaat behemah v'kelim,
and a ring made for an animal either to ornament an animal
or this was the debate even if you use it to control
the animal maybe that's considered a human ring but anyway sometimes rings
made for animals that aren't used by humans וכלים v'kelim or a
ring for a vessel like you put a ring on a vessel
for ornamentation ושאר כל הטבעות v'shear kol hatabaot or all of the
rings not used directly by humans טהורות tehorot are tahor טהור. tahor.
So of course there is a difference for rings even by tumah
טומאה tumah and tahorah טהרה. tahorah. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says
no, כי קאמר ליה איהו נמי דאדם קאמר ליה, ki ka'amar leh
ihu nami d'adam ka'amar leh, when he said all rings are the
same for tumah טומאה tumah and tahorah טהרה tahorah he meant people's
rings, not other types of rings. ודאדם דבר אחת היא, v'd'adam davar
achat hi, is it really true that all people's rings are the
same? והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in the mishna משנה, mishna, טבעת שהתקינה
לחקור בה מתנב ולקשור בה בכתפי כתף, tabaat shehitkina lachkor bah matnav
v'lakshor bah kitfei katef, if you have a ring that is used
as a type of to hook let's say you know parts of
a of a belt of an apron on or parts of a
cape on like to either you know to hook together parts of
clothing so טהורה tehorah it's tahor טהור. tahor. ולא אמרו טמאה, v'loh
amru t'mea, when do we say a ring was tamei טמא, tamei,
אלא שעולה אצבע בלבד, ela she'ola etzba bilvad, only on your finger.
Now it's a little bit of a surprise why should a ring
that's essentially used as a type of a belt or hook be
tahor טהור, tahor, it's a vessel כלי, kli, it's used as part
of clothing, so Rashi רש"י Rashi clarifies as Rashi רש"י Rashi did
yesterday when the issue came up about rings that when it's attached
to the clothing yes it is tamei טמא, tamei, it's part of
clothing and it's tamei טמא, tamei, the issue is when it is
detached from the clothing. So you have a ring that when you
can hook it into clothing but right now it's right now it's
separate. So is this a vessel כלי, kli, is this usable by
itself? And the answer is no, it has no use by itself,
it's only use usable when you attach it to clothing. But in
its current state it's not usable so it's not a vessel כלי,
kli, it's only usable to go on clothing but it's not directly
usable by you. Whereas a normal finger ring is something usable by
you in its current state and therefore it is tamei טמא. tamei.
So you see rings even for humans
are not all the same. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, you
can probably guess what's coming up, כי קאמר ליה איהו נמי דאצבע
קאמר ליה, ki ka'amar leh ihu nami d'etzba ka'amar leh, ah when
he said all rings are the same he didn't mean all rings
are the same, he meant finger rings are all
the same. ודאצבע דבר אחת היא, v'd'etzba davar achat hi, is it
really true that all finger rings are the same? והתנן, vehatnan, we
taught in the mishna משנה, mishna, טבעת של מתכת וחותמה של אלמוג,
tabaat shel matechet v'chotama shel almog, if you have a metal ring
with a cedar seal signet טמאה, t'mea, it's tamei טמא tamei because
then it's basically the ring is defined by the circular part of
it, by the part that goes around the finger and if that's
metal so a metal vessel כלי kli is tamei טמא. tamei. ושל
אלמוג וחותמה של מתכת, v'shel almog v'chotama shel matechet, if it's made
of cedar and it has a metal seal טהורה, tehorah, it's tahor
טהור tahor because then it's a wooden vessel כלי kli if it's
made of cedar and a wooden vessel כלי kli is not tamei
טמא tamei unless it has a receptacle and this does not have
a receptacle. So you see not all rings are the same, it
depends if it's wood or if it's metal. So the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says you can probably guess what's coming
up, כי קאמר ליה איהו נמי כולה של מתכת קאמר ליה, ki
ka'amar leh ihu nami kula shel matechet ka'amar leh, he meant all
metal rings are the same. All metal rings for fingers are the
same, but for Shabbat שבת Shabbat there's a difference if it has
a seal or not a seal whether you can carry it on
Shabbat שבת. Shabbat. Okay. ועוד שאלה, V'od she'ela, that was story one.
The reason we brought it in because of the... the discussion of
rings for people versus rings for animals. ועוד שאל *Ve'od sha'al*, and
he also asked, שמעתי שחולקין בין מחט למחט *shamati shecholkin bein machat
lemachat*, I hear there is a difference between different types of needles.
אמר ליה Amar lei: *amar leih*, שמא לא שמעת לענין שבת Shabbat.
*shema lo shamata le'inyan Shabbis*, maybe you heard regarding שבת Shabbat. *Shabbis*
because by שבת Shabbat. *Shabbis* if you carry out a normal needle
with an eye in it then it's carrying. If however it's a
needle without an eye and that's made as a type of an
ornament like you would sometimes put like a pin or a needle
in your like garment, right, then it's a type of a תכשיט
tachshit, *tachshis*, ornament, and it is not a problem or at least
you're not חייב *chayav* if you wear it on שבת Shabbat *Shabbis*.
So yes, by שבת Shabbat, *Shabbis* there's a difference. ואילו לענין טומאה
*Ve'ilu le'inyan tumah* because when it comes to טומאה *tumah*, דא ודא
אחת היא *da veda achas hi*, all needles are the same. ולענין
טומאה דא ודא אחת היא *Ule'inyan tumah da veda achas hi*? So
is it really true for טומאה *tumah* all are the same? והתנן
*Vehatnan*, מחט שניטל חורה או עוקצה *machat shenital churah o uktzah*, if
you have a needle that either its eye, its hole, or its
point has been removed, so it's no longer functional, טהורה *tehorah*, it's
טהורה *tehorah*. So you see they're not all the same, that would
not be able to become טמא tamei *tamei*, it's no longer functional.
So כי קאמר *ki ka'amar*, now when did he say it's all
the same? בשלמה *bishleimah*, if it's a complete needle. ובשלמה דא ודא
אחת היא *Uvishleimah da veda achas hi*? Is it really true that
all whole needles are the same? והתנן *Vehatnan*, we taught in the
משנה Mishna *mishna*, מחט
שהעלתה חלודה *machat she'alsah chaludah*, so if you have a needle that
got rusty, אם מעכב את התפירה טהורה *im me'akev es hasefirah tehorah*,
if it prevents sewing it's טהורה *tehorah*, it's not functional, ואם לאו
טמאה *ve'im lav tameia*, if not it's טמאה *tameia*. ואמרי דבי רבי
Rebbe, ינאי *Ve'amari devei Rabbi Yannai*, and in the house of רבי
ינאי *Rabbi Yannai* they explained, והוא שרישומו ניכר *vehu sherishumo nikar*, only
if its mark is noticeable. The way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* explains this
means if you sew with it, it leaves a stain because of
the mark, then it's considered not usable. Okay, because of the, I
mean because of the rust. If the rust leaves a stain behind,
then obviously it's no longer usable. Anyway, you see that there could
be a whole needle that is not טמא *tamei* because you wouldn't
use it because of the rust. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says,
no, כי קאמר ליה בשיפא קאמר ליה *ki ka'amar leih beshipa ka'amar
leih*. When he said that all needles are the same, it meant
a whole polished needle, a whole non-rusty needle, all of those are
the same. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ובשיפא דא ודא אחת
היא *uvishipa da veda achas hi*? Is it really true that whole
polished needles are all the same? והתניא *Vehatanya*, we taught in the
ברייתא braita, *Beraisa*, מחט *machat*, a needle, בין נקובה בין אינה נקובה
*bein nekuvah bein einah nekuvah*, whether it has a hole in it
or not a hole in it, מותר לטלטלה בשבת *mutar letaltelah beShabbos*,
you can move it on שבת Shabbat *Shabbis*. So while for carrying
there's a difference if it has a hole or not, that if
it has a hole it's considered a needle and you're carrying on
שבת Shabbat, *Shabbis*, without a hole it maybe is a different type
of an ornament, of a jewelry, and it's not a problem of
carrying. But when it comes to moving it in the house, מוקצה
muktzah. *muktzeh*, it doesn't matter if it has a hole or not.
In either case it's considered a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli shemelachto le'issur*,
a vessel that's used for איסור *issur*, for sewing, let's say in
a worst case scenario, even if it has a hole in it.
But fine, you're allowed to use that לצורך עצמו ולצורך מקומו *letzorech
atzmo uletzorech mekomo*, you can use it for its own purpose. So
if you want to use the needle for, I don't
know, picking your teeth, you can do that on שבת Shabbat *Shabbis*.
Okay, it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli shemelachto le'issur*, normally used for
איסור *issur*, you can use it for לצורך היתר *letzorech hetter*. So
for מוקצה muktzah. *muktzeh*, whether it has a hole or not, even
if it's normally used for sewing, you can move it in your
house on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbis*. Okay, ולא אמרינן נקובה *velo amrinan nekuvah*,
when does it matter if it has a hole in it? אלא
Ella, לענין טומאה בלבד *ela le'inyan tumah bilvad*, when it comes to
טומאה *tumah* only, that with a hole it's considered a vessel, an
eye meaning, without an eye it's not considered a vessel. So here
you see the exact same difference you make for carrying on שבת
Shabbat *Shabbis*, that it's considered carrying when it has an eye and
not when it doesn't have an eye, we make the same difference
for טומאה *tumah*. When it has an eye it's a vessel, when
it doesn't have an eye it's not a vessel. So how can
you say that by טומאה *tumah* it makes no difference, it's all
the same? So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, התרגמה אביי אליבא דרבא
*Hattargemah Abaye aliba deRava*, אביי *Abaye* explained it according to רבא *Rava*,
בגלמי *begalmi*, when it is an unformed needle. Meaning that you have
not finished making the needle. You had like a long, you know,
I don't know, string, whatever like stick of, you know, metal, and
you're breaking off pieces to make it fashioned into needles, and you
haven't yet and you maybe are sharpening the edge and you haven't
yet made the eye. So when you haven't yet made the eye,
it's not a vessel for טומאה *tumah*. Okay, so that's why for
טומאה *tumah* there is a difference, it's true, when it's as of
yet unfashioned. But when he said all needles were the same for
טומאה *tumah*, it meant finished needles. Even for finished you have two
types. You have a needle that has an eye in it and
you have a needle that doesn't have an eye, it's more like
a pin that's used for ornamentation. So when they're both finished, except
one has an eye and one doesn't, for טומאה *tumah* they're all
considered a vessel and they're all טמא *tamei*. For שבת Shabbat *Shabbis*
there's a difference because one is an ornament, there are two types
of vessels, an ornament, which wearing it on שבת Shabbat *Shabbis* is
not carrying, and the other is a type of a thing for
sewing, which it would be considered carrying on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbis*, it's
not made for wearing. Okay, so that's all the end of wrapping
that up. And the point here that we're seeing though is an
ongoing questioning and comparison of laws of on the one hand carrying
and also laws of מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh* on the one hand versus
laws of טומאה וטהרה *tumah vetaharah*. These are all areas where the
definition of vessel matters, but the question is, is it the same
definition or not? And here we are seeing that there are differences
between these categories. Okay, now we move on to the next משנה
Mishna, *mishna*, four lines from the bottom on נב עמוד ב *nun
beis amud beis*, getting closer to where today's דף *daf* begins, which
gets us back to what types of things can animals wear on
שבת Shabbat, *Shabbis*. And the basic rule being that they can wear
things that are there to sort of control them or protect them,
but not things that are deemed as superfluous, those would be considered
a משא *massa*. So it says the following: חמור Chamor, יוצא במרדעת,
be'marda'at a חמור,
a donkey can go out with a saddle on,
a saddle cloth. They have a very nice picture of that in
Steinsaltz. Okay, so not actually the saddle, but a type of a
cloth that would go on the donkey underneath the saddle, a saddle,
in order like keep it warm or to and therefore it can
go out with this saddle cloth בזמן שקשורה בו, bisman she'kshura bo,
if it's tied to the donkey. Why if it's not tied? We'll
see in a minute. זכרים, Zacharim, rams, יוצאים בלבובין, yotzim bilvuvin, can
go out בלבובין bilvuvin bound. We'll see what that means in the
גמרא. Gemara. Basically, one explanation will be that it means with their
genitals covered, the other with their hearts covered, and this would be
a standard type of a thing. ורחלות, U'rechelot, sheep, יוצאות שחוזות כבולות
וקבונות. yotzot shachuzot, kevulot, u'kevunot. So these are three different ways of
binding things onto sheep. One means holding up, meaning a female sheep,
one is holding up their fat tail in order to make them
more accessible for copulating with the rams, the other is binding down
their fat tail to prevent them from copulating, and the קבונות kevunot
is with their like wool covered in order to protect the wool.
All of those are normal ways of sheep going out. העזים יוצאות
צרורות, Ha'izim yotzot tzerurot, goats go out also bound, with as we'll
see in the גמרא Gemara means bound basically for, well we'll see
different reasons, but basically it's like nursing in order to prevent them
from from milking or to prevent their, you know, the udders and
the nipples from scraping against the ground. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose
omer, אוסר בכולן, oser be'chulan, Rabbi Yose forbids all these cases חוץ
מן הרחלים הקבונות, chutz min ha'rechelim ha'kevunot, with the exception of the
sheep that are going out with their wool protected. רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda says, עזים יוצאות צרורות ליבש, izim yotzot
tzerurot leyavesh, they can go out bound with their udders bound if
you're doing it to cause them to dry up from their udders,
that they're already done nursing and you don't want them to continue
to nurse, אבל לא לחלב, aval lo lachalav, not if you're or
לחלב, lechalav, not if you're trying to do it because they're still
nursing and you're trying to catch the milk and not let the
milk go to waste. Why these things should matter we will discuss
as we deal with them one by one in the גמרא. Gemara
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Yes. So what happens
if your animal does one of these things? Are they guilty of
a מלאכה? Melacha? No, no, no, so no, no, so it's about
you, obviously, it's a commandment on you and I actually want to
make a mention of this because you know most of this פרק
Perek does seem like to us like on the one hand very
technical and we don't really
understand, we barely know, speaking personally, about what all the different animals
are,
let alone what all these different saddlebags and saddles and all these
things are, but besides which it also seems it's very like irrelevant
to us because this isn't part of our שבת. Shabbat, But if
you actually think about it, I was thinking about it the other
day, you know, תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion at various points,
how do we rule here, how do we rule here? For him
it was very relevant. They had horses, they had cows, they had
to know. And if you think about it, it like, you know,
what it meant to worry about this before שבת. Shabbat Like we're
right now in the middle of the פרקים Prakim that deal with
getting ready for שבת. Shabbat So first we have במה מדליקין, Bameh
Madlikin, lighting the candles, then we have the whole stuff about putting
stuff on the fire before שבת Shabbat or insulating it. And now
we're dealing with making sure that your animals don't have things on
them they can't have on them on שבת, Shabbat. which means every
ערב שבת Erev Shabbat would entail you doing what? Going down to
your stables, going down to the barn, making sure that all of
these extraneous things were off of your animals. So not working your
animals on שבת Shabbat, did not just mean not taking out your
donkey and putting a load on it or plowing with your cow.
It actually meant like, you know, taking things off of your animals
that would make them have more of a שבת, Shabbat. you know,
free them up and remove this extraneous stuff from them. So I
think to me that's like very powerful thinking about what it meant
to create שבת Shabbat, not just for you but, you know, for
even all of your animals. So but the answer is though, if
you didn't do this and they had this stuff on and they
went into רשות הרבים, Reshut Ha'rabim, you would violate the prohibition of
making sure your animals didn't work on שבת. Shabbat But it would
be you who would violate. But if you think about what it
means that it's not that that means like you have to consciously
make sure that all of your animals are not, you know, are
sort of don't have this extraneous stuff on, you know, that would
really be and I think that's like powerful to think about that
as a type of a way you prepare for שבת Shabbat. and
what it means to have שבת Shabbat, throughout the house. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. So אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, והוא שקשורה
מערב שבת. ve'hu she'kshura me'erev Shabbat. The משנה Mishna says that this
this saddle cloth has to be tied up. He says only if
it's tied up ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. אמר רב נחמן מתניתין נמי
דייקא, Amar Rav Nachman matnitin nami dayka, that's you can be inferred
that from the משנה, Mishna, דקתני, de'katni, the משנה Mishna says, the
next משנה, Mishna because the next משנה Mishnah is also sort of
the mirror image of these. It says you can can can can
do these cases and then the next set of משניות Mishnayot says
you can't do all the following and you can't do is pretty
much the inverse of everything you could do. So here it says
you can go out with a bound saddle, you know, saddle cloth.
So next משנה Mishna says אין החמור יוצא, Ein ha'chamur yotzei, a
donkey cannot go out במרדעת with a saddle cloth בזמן שאינה קשורה
לו, bisman she'eina kshura lo, and it's not bound up to it.
היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא שאינה קשורה לו כלל,
ileima she'eino keshurah lo klal, if it's not bound at all, פשיטא,
peshita, obviously you can't go out with a completely loose saddle cloth.
Why? דילמא נפלה ליה, dilma nafla lei, because then it'll fall off,
it's likely to fall off ואתי לאתויי, ve'ati le'atuyei, and you'll come
to carry it. So this is important. There are two reasons why
animals can't wear certain things and two reasons we'll find out in
the next פרק perek that deals with what people can and can't
wear. Two reasons. One is that the thing itself is not considered
clothing or an ornament or for an animal it's not normal to
be on, it's not a protection, then then it's considered carrying. Even
though it's on your body, it's still a form of carrying. If
I have a knapsack on, for example, to take an extreme example,
even though it's on my body, it's still I'm carrying something on
my body. So you have to define for humans what's considered clothing
and and sort of jewelry as opposed to anything that isn't is
considered a type of a carrying. By an animal, it's normal things
that are normally worn or things that are normally there to protect
is a type of a clothing, anything else is a משאוי, masoi,
is carrying. So that's one category of things you can't have on
you on שבת Shabbat when when you go out to the street
on שבת. Shabbat, But the other thing is something that isn't carrying,
but you might come to take it off or might come to
fall off, and then you'll accidentally wind up carrying. So when we
get to the case by the humans, by the next פרק, perek,
people will see that it's all these types of like jewelry, you'll
take it off to show your friends this nice piece of jewelry,
and then you'll forget to put it back on and you'll come
to carry it. Okay, as I mentioned before, that's why some places
have a practice if there's no עירוב eruv you don't wear gloves,
because you'll come to take off your glove and shake somebody's hand
and then you'll forget to put your glove back on. So one
is דאורייתא de'oraita and one is דרבנן. derabanan. Yes, exactly. The first
one is a biblical problem, the second one is rabbinic. So here
too by animals, same story. If something is very loose, and you
had this yesterday, probably like the halter of a goat, and it'll
come to fall off, then it's a problem because you might come
per se it's not a problem, but rabbinically it's a problem, it
might come to fall off, you might come to carry it. So
the גמרא Gemara, says if this saddle cloth is not tied, then
of course you can't have it, you know, have it on on
שבת, Shabbat? it'll easily fall off, you'll come to carry it. So
אלא לאו, ela lav, so why does it have to say not
tied? שאינה קשורה מערב שבת, she'eino keshurah me'erev Shabbat, it means that
as long as it's not tied on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, it's
going to be a problem even if you were to tie it
on שבת, Shabbat, no good. מכלל, michlal, and from that you can
infer דרישא, de'reisha, when it says when it's tied it's okay, שקשורה
לו מערב שבת, she'keshurah lo me'erev Shabbat, it means tied from already
before שבת Shabbat begins, שמע מינה, shma mina, we taught similarly. Now,
why does it matter whether it was tied when שבת Shabbat. begins
or not? So there's like a whole different set of explanations. רש"י
Rashi says well, if you waited till שבת Shabbat to tie it,
then it seems like you're doing it specifically as a means of
carrying this thing,
not as a means of it just being on the animal to
protect it, which is interesting because we don find that in other
cases that it necessarily matters when it went on to define whether
it's considered protection or carrying, but maybe different contexts mean something different.
תוספות Tosafot says a similar type of an issue, that when you
not that it becomes a type of a carrying, but it makes
it look to people like you're planning on sort of having
it, you're planning on transporting it. Meaning it not basically the same
idea as רש"י Rashi says, except rather than saying halachically its definition
becomes a burden, it's just that it appears to people like that's
your intention and that's a problem. Then the final answer תוספות Tosafot
gave is very interesting. He says also about impression, the last line
of the תוספות Tosafot וזהו, ve'zehu, he says, ורב פורת פירש דמיחזי
כאילו מתכוון להוליך בהמה למקום רחוק. ve'Rav Porat peireish de'meichezi ke'ilu mitkaven
le'holich beheimah le'makom rachok. If
people see you, and this is important because this will come up
in a number of contexts about things with your animal, that it
looks it looks like a very weekday activity. You could describe this
as מראית עין, marit ayin, or you could describe this as just
it sort of it violates the spirit of שבת. Shabbat. There I
am, I'm in my barn or wherever you keep your donkeys, I'm
out there by with my donkey, I've got the saddle thing on
it and I'm tying it on on שבת, Shabbat? that looks like
what I do during the week, as I load up my donkey,
I put the stuff on, I'm getting ready to go on a
trip. So even if it's not an issue of carrying, it looks
like I'm about to get my donkey ready for a trip and
start going on some trip on שבת. Shabbat Now, that could be
a problem because of מראית עין, marit ayin, like it looks like
you're doing something wrong, but as I said we will see a
number of places this comes up with the animals, and I would
say it's more than מראית עין. marit ayin. It's that it creates
it's like, you know, עובדא דחול, uvda de'chol, it creates a weekday
type of an experience on שבת, Shabbat? you don't want to be
binding these things. So therefore they only allowed it when it was
from before שבת Shabbat? and not when it was on not to
do it on שבת. Shabbat Yes.
Right, because you take off everything at night?
Right.
So then so then if you took it off including the saddle
cloth, you would take that off every night? So then you've got
a problem. Then if you want to have it on on שבת,
Shabbat you have to take care of it before שבת Shabbos begins.
So it's an interesting point.
Yes, so they raise the issue of you're out there and you
tie up the saddle, would would it
also maybe lead
you to do other prohibited things on שבת, Shabbos. like making a
knot on שבת? Shabbos.
Yes, so that's interesting. You could have certainly said that you're not
allowed to make certain knots on שבת, Shabbos, so you know, I
don't know, maybe this was something with a belt with a buckle
and not really with a knot, but yes, you could. You could
have said that, that maybe there's certain types of way you prepare
it and it involves making other types of knots that are prohibited.
Yes, you could have suggested that as well. Because my question was
more like would you by doing it would you start thinking okay
it's not really
ship- it's not שבת Shabbos.
to do this and then
turn around and do something else? Yeah so that's right. That could
be. Normally we're sort of concerned about those more in like the
immediate context, not like it'll lead to two, you know, five minutes
from now you'll still have
that
thing in mind.
But I haven't seen it. Normally when we have those concerns, it's
more like in that immediate context, you'll come to do- you'll come
to like forget it's שבת. Shabbos. But that could be. You could
still raise that issue, making other knots, doing other types of things,
you know, who knows?
Yes, yes. Because it's a debate about whether... of those opinions says
it's not intended to happen, you can rely on doing the action.
Right. So how- how far can we apply that thing? Like this
idea of something falling off, you didn't intend it to happen but
yes, so
the falling off isn't a problem. The problem is is that you'll
pick it up and you'll carry it and you'll forget it's- and
you'll forget it's שבת Shabbat. or something, which is actually similar to
the point that Paula makes. And that's not- not intending is when
you're doing action A and action B may or may not result.
Here, if it falls off and you pick it up and you
walk- and you walk with it because you forgot that there's no
עירוב eruv or something like that, so that's a classic case of
שוגג. shogeg. You're intentionally doing the act, you just forgot that it
was שבת.
Shabbat. Okay, yeah. I- I got a text message from Michael. How
do you watch the דף יומי Daf Yomi stream? Is it YouTube,
YUTorah channel?
Yeah. Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. It says
like this. Okay. So it says, where are we? תניא נמי הכי.
Tanya nami hachi. We taught similarly. חמור יוצא במרדעת בזמן שקשורה לו
מערב שבת. Chamor yotzei be'marda'at bizman she'kshurah lo me'erev Shabbat. The donkey
can go out with this saddle cloth if it's bound from ערב
שבת. Erev Shabbat. ולא באוכף V'lo be'uchaf but not with a saddle
itself, אף על פי שקשורה לו מערב שבת, af al pi she'kshurah
lo me'erev Shabbat, even though it's ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, because that's
not done to keep the animal warm or to protect the animal,
that's done for- riding the animal. For riding the animal, right? And
something done for using the animal is considered a burden. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר אף באוכף בזמן שקשורה לו מערב שבת. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, af be'uchaf bizman she'kshurah lo me'erev Shabbat. You know
what? You can even have a saddle on it if it's tied
from ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. ובלבד שלא יקשור לו מסריכין ובלבד שלא
יקשור לו רצועה תחת הזנב. U'vilvad she'lo yikshor lo masrichin u'vilvad she'lo
yikshor lo retzuah tachat ha'zanav. You can however not use the straps
that keep it- that sort of keep it close to the neck
or the back sort of straps that go under the tail. Again,
there's a nice picture in Steinsaltz, but basically you would have those
types of straps if you were trying to keep the saddle on
because you were really going to go riding it. And therefore when
it goes up on an incline, you don't want it to- to
slide back, and when it goes down, you don't want it to
slide forward, so you've got straps in the front and the back.
So if you put on those types of straps, it makes it
very clear that you're putting on the saddle because you're planning on
going for a trip or planning on loading it up with a
burden. But otherwise, the saddle might be something legitimate. Not exactly clear
though why it's legitimate. I mean, what do you need a saddle
for to protect the animal? But as we'll see later, maybe saddles
were used also as ways for keeping it warm, another type of
thing on it. So let's take a look. Okay, one minute. So
that- but רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says normally you can as long
as you don't tie down these straps, which makes it clear that
or indicate that you're going to put a burden on it. בעי
מיניה רב אסי בר נתן מרבי חייא בר רב אשי. Boei minei
Rav Assi bar Natan me'Rabbi Chiyya bar Rav Ashi. So רב אסי
בר נתן Rav Assi bar Natan asked רבי חייא בר רב אשי.
Rabbi Chiyya bar Rav Ashi. מהו ליתן מרדעת גבי חמור בשבת? Mahu
litein marda'at gavay chamor be'Shabbat? Can you put a- this- this saddle
cloth on the donkey on שבת? Shabbat. Now it's clear from our
משנה and from גמרא Gemara earlier discussion that you can only if
it's tied from before שבת Shabbos. can you go out with it.
But רש"י Rashi says and it'll be clear from the גמרא, Gemara
the question is not to go out on רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
The question is can you even put down this saddle cloth just-
it's in your own backyard and there's no carrying issue, you just
want to keep the donkey warm, can you do it on שבת?
Shabbat Okay, so what should the issue be? Why can't you do
it on שבת? Shabbat, Okay, so a couple of different possibilities that
are raised. רש"י Rashi says maybe it looks like- it- again, it
looks to people if you're putting it on on שבת Shabbat. even
if you're not taking it out into the street, it looks like
you're getting it ready for some trip or to carry. תוספות Tosafot
says more thinks that the concern is- and this seems to be
the most the thing that ties all of the ongoing discussion together-
that- that it's just effort. There's a question about the גמרא Gemara
has this in a couple of times, how much effort can you
exert on שבת Shabbat. for your animals? Obviously you can feed them,
you can do things to keep them warm, but how much effort
is considered to just be, even if it's not a מלאכה melachah
per se, you know, too much effort for your animals? Again, it's
sort of like weekday activities, that you're, you know, spending all this
time taking care of your animals. So obviously, you can do things
that are for the basic need, but how much is too much?
That's what תוספות Tosafos sees as the issue. So here's his question.
Forget carrying, forget going into the street. Even in your backyard, can
you put a saddle cloth on your donkey? אמר ליה מותר. Amar
lei mutar. He says, yeah, fine, no problem. אמר ליה: amar lei
so he said back to him, ומה בין זו לאוכף? u'mah bein
zu l'uchaf? How is this different from a saddle? a saddle, you
can't put a saddle on your donkey even if you're keeping it
in your backyard. אישתיק. Ishtik. He was silent; he didn't have an
answer. אותיביה. Eisvei. So he thought the reason he didn't give an
answer was maybe he said you could also do a saddle. So
he says, look, I'll show you you can't do a saddle. אוכף
על גבי החמור, Ukkaf al gabei ha-chamor, with the saddle for the
donkey לא יטלנו בידו, lo yitlenu be-yado, you can't even move it.
It's מוקצה. muktzah, So, and, so what do you do if you've
got your saddle on your donkey on שבת Shabbat and you want
to get it off the donkey? So what do you do if
you're not allowed to move? מוליכו ומביאו בחצר, Moli-kho u-mevi-o be-chatzer, you
move the donkey back and forth in your yard והיא נופל מאליה
ve-hi nofel me-elei-ha and it'll fall off. But so what do you
see? I mean, you see that a saddle is מוקצה. muktzah. So
certainly you're not allowed to put it on the donkey. So why
can you not—why is a saddle מוקצה muktzah. and you can't put
it on, but the saddle cloth is okay? Okay, now again, if
the issue was that it was looking like you're about—like a burden,
there's an obvious difference between the saddle and the saddle cloth, right?
Saddle looks much more like you're going for a ride and you're
going to load it up as opposed to the saddle cloth. So
therefore, it makes more sense to read the גמרא Gemara that said
the concern is not that it looks like a burden, the concern
is you're just doing it as a way of warming the donkey
and is this considered taking, you know, too much of an effort
for your animal? And he says, look, if a saddle cloth is
okay, why should a saddle be any different? So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara continues. So the גמרא Gemara, says like this. השתא
ליטול אמרת לא, Hashta litol amart lo, you said you can't even
move it, לאנוח מיבעיא? le-ani'ach mibaya? Is there any question that you
can't put a saddle on? So I'm back to my question: what's
the difference between the saddle and the saddle cloth? So אמר ליה
Amar lei, רבי זירא, Rebbi Zeira, so רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira said
back to the one who was challenging him, רב אסי, Rav Assi,
he said to him, הנח לשבתי, Hana-ch le-shavtei, leave Reb Chiya alone.
כרביה סבירא ליה, Ke-rabbeih sevira lei, he holds like his רבי, like
רב. Rav. דאמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב, De-amar Rebbi Chiya
bar Ashi amar Rav, because Rebbi Chiya bar Ashi, the one who
was being asked this question, said in the name of רב, Rav,
תולין טרסקא לבהמה בשבת, Tolin traska le-vehema be-Shabbos, you can tie a
feed basket to an animal on שבת. Shabbat Have you ever seen
those horses? They've got a nice picture in Steinsaltz. You know, a
horse with like this bucket that it's sort of its whole mouth
is in it and it eats from the bucket, makes it very
easy, doesn't have to bend down to eat. You can do that
for an animal on שבת. וכל שכן למרדעת, Ve-kol she-ken le-marda'as, and
certainly you can put on the saddle cloth. Now, what are you
doing this for? Also to take care of your animal. There's no
מלאכה, melachah, there's no issue of a burden, it's in your backyard.
Okay, you're doing it to take care of your animal. So now
putting the feed basket on it is just making life a little
bit easier for it. I mean, you could put feed on the
ground, it would have to bend down, but you can nevertheless go
to this effort just to make it a little easier for it,
the animal doing less work. So if you can do an effort
for that just to make it a little easier, you can certainly
put on a blanket on it, a saddle blanket, which actually is
doing something more needed for the animal, it's keeping it warm. So
that's why it's a כל שכן למרדעת. kol she-ken le-marda'as. If you
can do the feed, you can certainly do this saddle blanket. ומה
התם דמשום תענוג שרי, U-mah hatam de-mishum ta'anug shari, the feed basket,
it's just making it more pleasurable, you're allowed to do that on
שבת, it's a legitimate effort, הכא דמשום צער לא כל שכן? hacha
de-mishum tza'ar lo kol she-ken? Here that it's because of pain, like
if it's, you know, if it's cold, how much more so should
you be able to put on the blanket? So again, the way
תוספות Tosafos reads it, which connects these ideas, is: what degree of
effort are you allowed? And he says if we're allowing you even
something that just is for pleasure for the animal, certainly we're going
to allow you for something that is to alleviate pain, to alleviate
cold, to put on a blanket. And presumably though, we still haven't
explained why the saddle itself is a problem. Presumably the saddle is
even less necessary than all of these. We will see it. Or
the saddle could be an external problem. The saddle could be like
it looks like you're about to go riding on it. But even
within this continuum, it could be the saddle does something even less
purposeful than this, which is giving it pleasure or alleviating pain. So
let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. שמואל אמר, Shmuel
amar, now שמואל Shmuel says, מרדעת מותר, marda'as mutar, the saddle cloth
is fine, that's keep it warm, וטרסקא אסור, ve-traska assur, the basket
is forbidden. That's an unnecessary effort. Again, all of this is not
that you're going out in the street, that you're doing it in
your backyard and it's just a question of effort, not a question
of burden. אזל רבי חייא בר יוסף אמר לשמעתא דרב קמיה דשמואל.
Azal Rebbi Chiya bar Yosef amar le-shma'ta de-Rav kameih de-Shmuel. So Rebbi
Chiya bar Yosef told over רב's Rav position to שמואל, Shmuel, which
is that not only can you do the saddle cloth, you can
even do the feed basket. אמר ליה, so שמואל Shmuel said to
him, אי הכי אמר אבא, ei hachi amar Abba, if that was
אבא, Abba, which is like my colleague said, לא ידע במילי דשבתא
ולא כלום. lo yada be-millei de-Shabbata ve-lo kelum. He doesn't know anything
about שבת. So he was pretty upset. Ha! He thinks you could
put a feed basket on a horse! So what? How ignorant can
you be? So anyway, doesn't seem to us like it would be
anyway what engendered that strong response. כי סליק רבי זירא, Ki salik
Rebbi Zeira, when רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira went to ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, אשכחיה לרב בנימין בר יפת, ashkecheih le-Rav Binyamin bar Yephet, he
saw רב בנימין בר יפת, Rav Binyamin bar Yephet, דיתיב וקאמר לה
משמיה דרבי יוחנן, de-yasiv ve-ka'amar lah mi-shmeih de-Rebbi Yochanan, that he was
telling over in the name of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan a similar
teaching. נותנין מרדעת על גבי חמור בשבת, Nosnin marda'as al gabei chamor
be-Shabbos, you can put a saddle cloth on a donkey on שבת.
About a saddle blanket on a donkey on שבת. אמר ליה יישר.
Amar lei yasher. You see, even then they had the יישר כח.
yasher koach. They have that as a phrase, which is like more
power to you. וכן תרגמה אריוך בבבל. V'chein tirgemah Arvach b'Bavel. That
is the way the king interprets in בבל. Bavel. That was a
nickname for שמואל Shmuel because he was like he had he was
a lot had a lot of authority. Also, he was very close
to the government. Anyway, so שמואל Shmuel says the same thing that
you can put a saddle blanket on a donkey on שבת. So
the גמרא Gemara says אריוך מנהו? Arvach manhu? Who is this אריוך?
Arvach? What does that refer to? שמואל. Shmuel. So that's שמואל. Shmuel.
והא רב נמי אמרה? Veha Rav nami amrah? One minute, רב Rav
also said you can put a saddle blanket on a donkey on
שבת. Why did he say that's what שמואל Shmuel says? אלא, it
must be he didn't just say that. He must have said not
just you can put a blanket, but you can only put a
blanket. שמעיה דהוה מסיים בה, Shama'i d'havah mesayeim bei, he ended by
saying ואין תולין תרסקא בשבת. v'ein tolin traska b'Shabbat. You can put
on the blanket, but not the feedbag. אמר ליה יישר. Amar lei
yasher. He said to him, ah, good, more power to you. וכן
תרגמה אריוך בבבל. V'chein tirgemah Arvach b'Bavel. That's what שמואל Shmuel says
in בבל, Bavel, that you can put on the blanket but not
the feedbag. So here again the question is how much effort can
you go if it's not strictly necessary, it's not cold, but you're
doing it to make it more convenient for the animal. And שמואל
Shmuel is making a distinction between how necessary it is. Now דכולי
עלמא מיהא, d'chuli alma miha, says the גמרא, Gemara everybody nevertheless says
מרדעת מותר. marda'at mutar. Now back to our question, what is the
difference between the blanket, the saddle blanket, and the saddle? מרדעת מותר.
marda'at mutar. מאי שנא מאוכף? Mai shna me'ukaf? How is it different
than the saddle? So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם דאפשר
דנפיל ממילא. shani hasam d'efshar d'nafal mimaila. The saddle is different. The
saddle it's possible that that will that will fall off, and if
it'll fall off, then maybe you'll come to carry it. Now that's
a pretty funny answer because first of all, if you strap it
in, how likely is it that it'll fall off? Number one. And
number two is maybe the strapping in you can't do. Maybe it
was just putting it on without strapping, right? The question was מהו
להניח. mahu l'hani'ach. So maybe the strapping was the problem we said
before, it looks like you're about to go on a trip. So
maybe says if you're putting it on without strapping, maybe there's a
more likely the saddle will fall. But even if the saddle will
fall, you're doing it in your backyard, why do I care? Right?
So it's not exactly clear why that is such a problem. Let's
take a look though, the גמרא Gemara will give another answer. So
let's take a look. רב פפא אמר כאן לחמם כאן לצננה. Rav
Papa amar kan l'chamam kan l'tzanenah. The difference is whether the blanket
is warming it up, that's an important purpose. The saddle somehow is
to keep is to cool it off. I have no idea how
putting on a saddle is supposed to cool it off. Okay, let's
take a look. לחמם אית ליה צערא. L'chamam isla tza'ara. If it
needs to be warmed and it's not being warmed up, then that's
pain and therefore you're allowed to put the saddle cloth on it.
לצננה L'tzanenah to cool it off, לית ליה צערא, leis lei tza'ara,
that's not so much pain if it just needs to cool off.
והיינו דאמרי אינשי Ve'hainu d'amrei inshi because people say חמרא אפילו בתקופת
תמוז קרירא ליה, chamra afilu b'tkufat Tammuz kariya lei, a donkey even
in the middle of the summer is cold for it. It's a
cold-blooded I guess cold-blooded animal. Is that true? No, it can't be,
it's a mammal. It's a mammal. Anyway fine, whatever. But anyway people
believe that donkeys were able to cool off their body easily, so
it's not so big such a big deal if it needs to
cool off. I honestly don't know how we think that putting a
saddle on a donkey makes it cool. Anyway, but these are someone
here says in the case of removing a saddle oh, so it's
to remove the saddle is to cool it off? But the question
was are you allowed to put the saddle on. Let me check
רש"י Rashi says מרדעת צריך לחמם מותר משום צערא, marda'at tzarich l'chamam
mutar mishum tza'ar, אבל... aval... oh, I'm sorry, רש"י Rashi says נטילת
אוכף אינו אלא לשיצטנן. netilat ukaf eino ela l'sheyitzanen. Okay, you're right,
I'm sorry, ולא שקלי ליה, v'lo shaklei lei, thank you, thank you,
at least that makes more sense. I forgot that the רש"י Rashi
had to remove the saddle is to cool it off. Okay, doesn't
still explain why you can't... the question was however putting the saddle
on. But I guess they're going on the ברייתא, braita the ברייתא
braita said if you wanted to remove the saddle you move it
around and you let it fall. So that was at least in
that ברייתא Braita the question was why you can't remove the saddle.
But the question was also why you can't put the saddle on.
Anyway, it's a funny גמרא Gemara because it goes so far to
saying that the saddle is מוקצה, it would seem that the most
obvious answer for all of this is the issue that saddle is
much more looks like you're about to go on a trip or
you're about to put a burden on more than any of these
other things and why isn't that a sufficient explanation of not taking
the saddle off or putting it on, you know, making it מוקצה.
But the גמרא Gemara seems to be giving these other explanations, and
that's one is that one relates to don't put it on because
it'll fall off easily, you're right, and the next one is don't...
I'm sorry, one minute... no, you know, רש"י Rashi says the same
thing about the earlier answer that it'll fall off easily. The reason
we don't want you to directly take it off is it's easy
enough for it to fall off. But if both of the answers
are explaining why we don't want you to take off the saddle,
they haven't really answered the question why we don't want you to
put on the saddle. Maybe again, maybe there the answer is more
obvious like I said, don't put on the saddle because it looks
like you're going on a trip, it looks like you're loading it
up with burden. Okay, so we have now you're allowed to put
on the blanket to keep it warm, that's not an undue effort.
There's a debate whether you can put on the feedbag. There's a
debate whether you can put on the feed basket, whether that's an
undue effort between רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. The saddle is completely
off limits, whether to put it on or to take it off.
Taking it off seems to be we don't have to allow you
to do it or it'll fall off or there's not a lot
to be lost because to cool it off, it can cool itself
off. Doesn't really get to the question why not to put it
on. As I said, maybe that's maybe that's implicit. Don't put it
on because that looks like, again, that you're loading it up and
a burden, even if you're only doing it in your backyard. Okay.
Or maybe you can't tie it. Well, no, the גמרא Gemara doesn't
say that. It sounds like don't handle the saddle at all. The
saddle's מוקצה. Oh, the the saddle blanket. Right, right. The saddle blanket.
Right. That's presumably, yeah, put it on and don't tie it. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי, Meitvei, I'll ask
you about this: לא יצא הסוס בזנב שועל. Lo yetzei hasus biznav
shual. Do not have a horse go out with literally a fox
tail. רש"י Rashi says it would be something that they would hang
from the head of the horse as a type of an ornament.
You know, sometimes you have, you see like a headdress on a
horse and they have anyway so apparently they would put some type
of like a fox tail on it. Don't do that. That's unnecessary
sort of ornamenting of the animal. ולא בזהורית שבין עיניו, V'lo biz'horit
shebein einav, or some type of like a red string between its
eyes. All of these are unnecessary ornamentations. Now, you know, the גמרא
Gemara also before yesterday spoke about a strap wrapped around the neck
or it spoke about a string between the horns of a cow
and that it said that if it was for ornamentation, it's a
problem, it's a burden. So it sounds like by all these גמרות,
Gemaras, and this is what תוספות says, that anything that's considered an
ornament for an animal is a burden, which is interesting. For people,
a תכשיט, jewelry, is considered a type of clothing. But for an
animal, ornamentation is seen as extraneous. It's like done maybe for human
needs. I want my animal to look nice, but it's not really
done for the animal. What does the animal care? It's got all
this, you know, נארישקייט narishkeit on it. So therefore so therefore it's
not it's considered carrying for the animal just because you want it.
The things have to be there for the sake of the animal,
not for the sake of the humans. That seems to be the
issue. Although רש"י Rashi seems to distinguish some type of ornamentation yes,
others no. And the רשב"א Rashba says for him maybe the issue
is just what's the norm as opposed to what's excessive. But it
seems like at least these senses that ornamentation is no good, that's
not really for the sake of the animal. So you cannot have
any of this stuff. Yes? I saw someone walking a dog and
the collar and the leash had these little LED lights on it.
So I'm thinking now, is that for safety or is it for
ornamentation? There you go, and that would be the difference about שבת.
The LED issue aside. Okay, so now says okay, so don't do
this. לא יצא הזב בכיס שלו. Lo yetzei hazav b'khis shelo. We
actually had this before way, way back. A person who has a
man who has some type of a זב, zav, a flow, a
penile emission, he cannot go out with a type of a something
to catch the flow because that's if you want to inspect it
to see if he's טמא or not, because that's not to protect
his body. If he's doing it so that he himself does not
get soiled, then it's acceptable, you know, then it's like a normal
function of clothing that you do it to protect your body. But
if he's doing it for the sake of catch of trapping it,
then it's not acceptable. ולא עזים בכיס שבדדיהן, V'lo izin b'khis shebadadeihem,
and not nursing goats with the type of a the receptacle underneath
their uterus, which is also there to catch the milk, and that's
also not acceptable. It's not a form of done for the protection
of the animal. ולא פרה בחסום שבפיה, V'lo parah b'khasum shebefiha, and
not a cow with the bit. Again, that's seen as excessive. It's
not needed strictly to protect the cow. ולא סיחין בתרסקלין שבפיהם, V'lo
syachin b'traskalin shebefihem, and not foals, young horses, with the baskets on
their mouth, לרשות הרבים. l'reshut harabim. You can't go out to the
public domain because that's seen again as excessive. Although that's done to
make life nice for them, right, it's an excessive type of a
thing. It's not something strictly needed. ולא בהמה בסנדל שברגליה, V'lo behemah
b'sandal sheberagleiha, and not a horse with its a horseshoe. Now that's
funny, you would think a horseshoe is so it doesn't get damaged,
that's very much necessary. So that last case is is technically actually
not a משאוי, masoi, it's okay from that perspective. But the problem
is is that there was a concern it would fall off and
you would come to carry it. Right, there's always that second rabbinic
category. So the last case actually is something that very much is
needed for the animal, but nevertheless they did not allow because of
a concern that it would fall off. ולא בקמיע, V'lo b'kame'a, and
not with a קמיע, kame'a, a charm, I what's the translation of
קמיע? kame'a? Amulet. Amulet, thank you, not with an amulet, which is
done to heal the animal. You have a sick animal, אף על
פי שהוא מומחה, af al pi shehu mumcheh, even though it was
done by an expert. וזה חומר בבהמה מבאדם, V'zeh chomer b'behemah mibe'adam,
it's more strict about animals about this than people. We'll see about
this in a minute. אבל יוצא הוא באגד שעל גבי המכה, Aval
yotzei hu b'eged she'al gabei hamakah, you or the animal can go
out with a bandage on your wound. or with a splint on
a broken leg, because that's considered to actually be something that is
like necessary, you know, for the animal or for the person and
therefore it's a type it's obviously considered something that I mean to
some degree some of these might even consider to be integrated into
the body and become like part of the leg if it's necessary.
But certainly it's as good as, you know, anything else that's done
to protect the animal. ובשליא המדולדלת בה, Uveshilya hamiduldelet bah, if it's
dragging an afterbirth, it has yet to expel its afterbirth, that's not
a problem, which is I don't know, maybe you know obviously considered
maybe still part of the animal. ופוקקים לו זוג בצווארה, Upokekim lo
zug betzavara, if it has a bell, you have to stop, you
know, you have to like seal up the bell so that it
no longer rings. It can't ring on שבת because then it sounds
like, you know, like it's making noise on שבת, sounds like you're
going to the market. ומטיילת עמו בחצר, Umetayelet imo bechatzer, and you
can have it walk with this bell in the courtyard, but you
cannot take it out into the street. Now the גמרא Gemara later
says, just a comment about the bell, we'll see more about that
later. Why can you not have it so the bell is stopped
up, it's not going to make its ringing sound, you know, a
cowbell, why can't you take it out in the street? So you
assume you can't take it out because it's not there to help
the animal, right? It's considered to be a so, you know, a
burden. Right, what function is it doing? The גמרא Gemara though says
the reason you can't take it out with it in the street
even if it's stopped up is people see you walking with your
Bessie with a bell around it, they think you're going to the
market. And that looks like a weekday activity. So one reason I
wanted to bring that out was again a concern about how it
appears. Not necessarily again a מראית עין, maris ayin, but might be
like weekday. You're walking in the street with your cow with a
bell, that feels like a very weekday type of an activity. It's
what you do when you go to the market. So that's that.
Now why didn't the גמרא just say that the bell is a
burden? So again this raises the question. The רשב''א Rashba says two
answers. One is, yeah, could have said that too, it just wanted
to make the other point. But yes, the bell's a burden. The
other answer is that no, sometimes ornamentation, like a bell, that if
it's the norm, it's not considered a burden. And then again becomes
the question: is the line between ornaments and other extraneous things versus
things that are strictly necessary to protect the animal, and it's also
categorical what function is it doing? Or is it much more, you
know, sort of the norm versus not the norm? And if the
bell is the norm, it wouldn't be a burden even if it's
not helping the animal at all. And the only reason it's a
problem is because it looks like you're going to the market. So
again, that's the ongoing question about what are the what's yes and
no in this whole in this whole פרק. perek. Is it burden,
is it sort of, you know, protecting the animal versus non and
therefore ornaments are no good? Or is it just things that are
the norm versus not the norm? Anyway, now we're going to go
back and look at some at look at the issue about the
about the feed basket. קתני מיהת, Katani mihat, we taught nevertheless, ולא
סייחין בתרסקל שבפיהם, Velo sayachin betraskal shebefihem, that these foals cannot go
out with the feed basket on their mouths. It says when? לרשות
הרבים, Lereshut harabbim, to the public domain. לרשות הרבים הוא דלא, Lereshut
harabbim hu delo, they can't go out into the public domain with
the feed baskets, that's considered excessive. הא בחצר שפיר דמי, Ha bechatzer
shapir dami, in your backyard it's okay. So so you see that
the feed basket is okay, and it proves like רב, Rav, that
it's okay to put a feed basket on an animal on שבת.
It's not an undue effort, not because of carrying, it's just not
an undue effort. מאי לאו בגדולים, Mai lav bigdolim, are we not
talking
about relatively large foals? I mean they're still foals but they're but
they're not just born. ומשום תענוג, Umishum ta'anug, and even though you're
doing it just for making life a little bit more pleasurable, you're
allowed to do this effort on שבת. גמרא says לא, בקטנים, Lo,
biktannim, no, we're talking about very young foals. ומשום צער, Umishum tza'ar,
if you've ever seen a young foal, it's got like its, you
know, a horse after it's just born, it stands up, it's like
a big animal, right? I mean for to have just been born,
and it's got long legs. So the concern is if it's got
long legs and not a big head, for that for that young
foal, it's a lot of effort to have to bend down to
eat and to eat the food. So for that foal, it's allowed.
It's not considered just pleasure for the animal, it's really alleviating some
real some real suffering, some real pain. ובקטנים ומשום צער, Uviktannim umishum
tza'ar, and it's because of the pain. So yes, you can do
this effort for animals on שבת when it is to alleviate pain.
But this feed basket would only be that for a very young
foal. דייקא נמי דקתני, Deika nami dekatani, that's also inferred from the
משנה from the ברייתא דקתני dekatani because it says דומיא דקמיע, dumya
dekameia, similar to the amulet. So we see we're doing something about
alleviating pain, not just of giving pleasure. שמע מינה, Shema mina, so
that's a good proof. So again, it seems like שמואל, Shmuel, at
least the way we're reading it, that things that are done for
the תענוג ta'anug of the animals is not a legitimate effort. אמר
מר, Amar mar, now let's look at some of these other cases.
Back to carrying, we're moving back and forth between going into the
street and in your backyard. In your backyard the concern is too
much effort, in the street it's a concern of being a burden.
ולא בקמיע, Velo bekameia, not with an amulet, אף על פי שהוא
מומחה, Af al pi shehu mumche, even though it's been like an
expert, it's been a tested amulet. גמרא says אנן תנן, Anan tenan,
ולא בקמיע שאינו מומחה, Velo bekameia she'eino mumche, that a person cannot
wear on שבת an untested amulet or an amulet written by a
non-expert. הא מומחה שפיר דמי, Ha mumche shapir dami, if it's been
tested, it's good. When we get to הכא נמי *hacha nami* שאינו
מומחה *she-eino mumcheh*. No, here too when you can go out with
an amulet, when you can't go out, or בהמה *behema*, an animal
can't wear an amulet, it's only a non-tested, non-expert amulet. הא אף
על פי שהוא מומחה קתני *ha af al pi she-hu mumcheh katani*,
but it says even though it's an expert, tested? No, מומחה לאדם
ואינו מומחה לבהמה *mumcheh le-adam ve-eino mumcheh le-behema*. It's been tested for
people, it hasn't been tested for animals. So an amulet that works
for people won't necessarily work for animals and that's why you can't
use it for animals. ומי איכא מומחה לאדם ולא הוי מומחה לבהמה
*u-mi ika mumcheh le-adam ve-lo havei mumcheh le-behema*? Is it really true
that if it can be tested for humans and work for humans
and not work for animals? אין *in*, yes. אדם דאית ליה מזלא
*adam de-it lei mazla*, a person that has luck, מסייע ליה *mesaye
lei*, so the amulet helps, can help, because a person anyway is
like more, you know, this is a general principle of the גמרא
*Gemara* that people more have luck than animals do. בהמה דלית לה
מזלא *behema de-leit lah mazla*, animals that don't have luck, לא מסייע
לה *lo mesaye lah*, the amulet will not help. So raises a
lot of interesting questions about amulets and, you know, superstition and so
on, we will bracket that for later when we get to amulets.
אי הכי *ei hachi*, says the גמרא *Gemara*, if that's true, מאי
דחומר בבהמה מביאדם *mai de-chomar bi-behema mi-be-adam*? If they're, if the only
reason it's not acceptable by an animal is it hasn't been tested
for an animal, why does it say that in this way animals
are more strict? They're not more strict, they both follow the same
rule, you could only use something that's been tested for that species.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, ניסבא דקמיע קאי *nisava de-kame'a kai*,
no, no, we're not comparing it to amulets. Amulets is basically the
same rule. Humans can use amulets tested for humans, animals can use
amulets tested for animals. So where do we say animals are more
strict? אסנדל קאי *a-sandal kai*, when it comes to wearing shoes. Humans
can wear shoes, right, hopefully, thankfully, in the way when they go
out, animals cannot because they will fall off again unless they've been
nailed in. Okay, תא שמע *ta shema*. Now we're still not done
with the רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* issue about doing an effort
for animals that's considered a תענוג *ta'anug*, a pleasure. סכין ומפרכסין לאדם
*sachin u-mefarchasin le-adam*, you can anoint and scrape a, like, a, you
know, a wound, not a wound, whatever, a scab, right, for a
person, ואין סכין ומפרכסין לבהמה *ve-ein sachin u-mefarchasin le-behema*, you can't do
it for an animal. So מאי לאו דאיכא מכה *mai lav de-ika
maka*? Presumably there still is the wound there and it's scabbed over,
ומשום צער *u-mishum tza'ar*, and it's because alleviating pain, and this is
a problem both to רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* that you can't
do this for an animal even though it alleviates pain? So even
alleviating pain is no good. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לא *lo*,
no, דגמר מכה *di-gemar maka*, the wound is healed, you still have
the scab left, but the wound is healed, ומשום תענוג *u-mishum ta'anug*,
but it's for pleasure. You know sometimes you scratch something it feels
good, it's not just because to alleviate pain. So therefore again this
is a proof like שמואל *Shmuel*, you cannot do certain things for
animals that are for pleasure, you can do certain things to alleviate
pain. תא שמע *ta shema*, come and hear. בהמה שאחזה דם *behema
she-achaza dam*, if an animal has like a blood clot, אין מעמידין
אותה במים בשביל שתצטנן *ein ma'amidin otah be-mayim bishvil she-titzztanen*, you don't
put it in water to cool off, which presumably would help it
unclot the blood. אדם שאחזו דם *adam she-achazo dam*, if a man
has it, מעמידין אותו במים בשביל שיצטנן *ma'amidin oto be-mayim bishvil she-yitztanen*,
you can put him in water. So אמר עולא *amar Ulla*, says
Ulla, גזירה משום שחיקת סממנים *gezeirah mishum shechikat samamanim*. No, that is
not because of an effort, that's a special concern that you're not
allowed to do certain types of רפואה *refuah* on שבת *Shabbat*, healing,
because we're afraid that it'll lead to grinding spices. So you know
you can't take medicine on שבת *Shabbat*, we're afraid it'll lead to
you making medicine and grinding not spices, but grinding the, you know,
the whatever the ingredients for the medicine. So the question becomes does
the prohibition of taking medicine apply to things that are not medicine
related, other types of things that are done for health? It's an
important question like if you have, you know, some OT that you've
got to do and you have to do certain stretches, are you
allowed, certain massages, are you allowed to do that on שבת *Shabbat*?
So here the גמרא *Gemara* initially, it'll change it in a minute,
I mean it's a very important question להלכה *le-halacha*, but anyway, initially
says no, that's included in being prohibited. So yes, effort you can
do for your animal on שבת *Shabbat*, but you cannot do רפואה
*refuah* for your animal on שבת *Shabbat*, although it's interesting your animal
might die, but maybe it's not to that degree. So let's see
where the גמרא *Gemara* goes with it. אי הכי *ei hachi*, if
that's why you can't do it for the animal, אדם נמי *adam
nami*, you shouldn't be able to do it for a man, for
a human. So again presumably it assumes that it's not life-threatening. So
if it's a רפואה *refuah* problem and you don't do it for
an animal, don't do it for a person. No, אדם נראה כמיקר
*adam nireh ke-meikar*, a person, he's going in the bath, looks like
he's just cooling off. It's not a heated bath, remember. So it's
not obviously it's a רפואה *refuah*. אי הכי בהמה נמי נראה כמיקר
*ei hachi behema nami nireh ke-meikar*? So okay, so the animal looks
like he's going to cool off. No, אין מיקר לבהמה *ein meikar
le-behema*. People don't, people don't immerse their animals in a thing of
water to cool them, the animal itself might walk into a pond,
but you would not do that with your animal unless the animal
was sick. So right now the reason we're saying it's not good
for the animal is because it's obvious type of a רפואה *refuah*.
So גמרא *Gemara* says ובהמה מי גזרינן *u-behema mi gazrinan*, are we
really concerned about animals about doing things that could lead to other
problems, like don't... to this it might lead to grinding medicine? והתניא
*Vehatanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *Baraita*, היתה עומדת חוץ לתחום *hayeta
omedet chutz litchum*, if your animal is outside of your תחום *tchum*,
of your how far you could go on שבת *Shabbos*, so קורא
לה והיא באה *koreh la vehia ba'ah*, you call it and it
comes to you. ולא גזרינן דלמא אתי לאתויי *Velo gazrinan dilma ati
le'asuyei*. So we're not concerned. Why do we let you do that?
Where we should be concerned that you'll step outside of your תחום
*tchum*. So you see that we're not—don't make these concerns, don't do
this by an animal you'll come to transgress. So we should let
you do this רפואה *refuah*, we should let you cool it off
and we shouldn't be concerned of what it would lead to. ואמר
רבינא *ve'amar Ravina*, it should be אמר *amar*, not ואמר רבינא *ve'amar
Ravina*. So רבינא *Ravina* says, because this seems to be the answer,
כגון שהיה תחום שלו מובלע בתוך תחום שלו *kegon shehayah tchum shelo
muvla betoch tchum shelo*. The case is no, you actually can go
to the animal, but the animal cannot go—the animal's space that the
animal can be moved is defined by where the shepherd was and
the shepherd had the animal when שבת *Shabbos* began, even though it's
your animal. So a case where the animal, if you consider it
like my shepherd was way out in the field and the animal
can only go like, you know, can only go up to the
end of this paper. I started my שבת *Shabbos* here, I can
go up to the end of the גמרא *Gemara*. And the animal
is right here. So I actually can walk over to the animal.
The only problem because it's within my תחום *tchum*. The only problem
is I can't bring the animal physically into—even if I'm not carrying
it like holding a rein and I'm walking it or whatever, it's
not a carrying issue. I can't bring it physically into my תחום
*tchum* because I'm taking the animal out of its legitimate space. So
we're not—so what I can do is I can call it and
it can come on its own. Okay? Your animal has a תחום
*tchum*? Yes, meaning it's not the animal's prohibited. I am prohibited of
taking vessels out of the space that is defined as their legitimate
space. And their space is defined as where the owner is, but
in the case of an animal's, it's defined where the shepherd of
those animals was when שבת *Shabbos* began. Okay, so if the shepherd
were here, then all the animals he was watching can only go
up to here. Okay, so therefore it says look, the reason I'm
not גוזר *gozer* there is because it's not so likely I'll do
something wrong. I can go where the animal is and I can
call the animal. The only thing I can't do is physically take
the animal. That we're not so concerned. So the basic answer seems
to be yes, but otherwise in general I would be concerned and
therefore I'm not going to let you put this animal into the
cold water because that is a concern about this whole medicine issue.
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar*, רב נחמן
בר יצחק *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak* says, שחיקת סממנים גופא תנאי היא
*shechikassammamim gufah tana'i hi*. No, there's a whole debate if this falls
into the category of the prohibited sort of רפואה *refuah* and medicine.
דתניא *Detanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *Baraita*, בהמה שאכלה כרשינים *behemah
she'achlah karshinim*, if an animal ate certain types of I don't know
כרשינים *karshinim*, some type of a grain that is not good for
it, what does it say? Vetch, it says vetch, there you go.
לא יריצנה בחצר בשביל שתתרפא *Lo yeritzennah bechatzer bishvil shetitrapeh*. Do not
sort of jog with it in the yard to get it to
sort of, you know, loosen its bowels and get the vetch out,
because that's a—that is basically a type of a רפואה *refuah* being
done for an animal. ורבי אושעיא מתיר *Verabbi Yoshi matir*, רבי אושעיא
*Rabbi Yoshi* said it's allowed. דרש רבא הלכה כרבי אושעיא *Darash Rava
halachah keRabbi Yoshi*, and רבא *Rava* said we rule like רבי אושעיא
*Rabbi Yoshi*. And רש"י *Rashi* says the difference here is that it's
not medicine, it's some other type of an effort, some other type
of a רפואה *refuah* but non-medicinal. And as I said, that is
an interesting question for people. Can you do stretches, can you do
certain exercise on שבת *Shabbos* that is non-medicinal but is done for
רפואה *refuah*? Okay, anyway, that's the end of the discussion about the
animals and the debate about רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* about doing
things for תענוג *ta'anug*. Let's try to get a little bit further.
Okay, אמר מר *amar mar*, לא יצא הזב בכיס שלו *lo yetze
hazav bekis shelo*, we discussed this before, a זב *zav* cannot go
out with the thing there to catch the flow because again it's
not to protect him. ולא עזים בכיס שבדדיהן *velo izim bekis shebedadeihen*,
or nursing goats with the thing under their—udders. והתניא יוצאות עזים בכיס
שבדדיהן *Vehatanya yotzos izim bekis shebedadeihen*? But we have a ברייתא *Baraita*
that says that they can go. Udders, thank you, what did I
say, uterus? Ay, thank you, udders, thank you. It's all whatever reproductive.
Anyway, udders. So אמר רב יהודה לא קשיא. הא דמהדק והא דלא
מהדק *amar Rav Yehuda lo kashya. Ha de'mehedak ve'ha de'lo mehedak*. It
depends if it's tight or it's not tight. Now presumably one difference
is, as רש"י *Rashi* says, if it's not tight, it'll fall off
and you'll come to carry it. Okay? But we'll see other differences
in a minute. רב יוסף אמר: תנאי שקלת מהעלמא *Rav Yosef amar:
Tana'i shechaltme'alma*? You're just grabbing random תנאים *tana'im* and you have a
contradiction? So there's an obvious answer here: it's not all the same
person. תנאי *Tana'i*, it's a debate of תנאים *tana'im*. דתנן *Detnan*, we
taught in the משנה *Mishnah*, העזים יוצאות צרורות *ha'izim yotzos tzruros*, the
goats go out bound, their udders bound. רבי יוסי אוסר בכולן *Rabbi
Yose oser bekulan*, רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* forbids, חוץ מן הרחלות הכבונות
*chutz min harchaleot hakevunot*, except for sheep covering their wool which we'll
discuss later. But he forbids in the case of the goats. רב
יהודה אומר *Rav Yehuda omer*, and רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* makes a
distinction. עזים יוצאות צרורות ליבש אבל לא לחלב *Izim yotzos tzruros leyabesh
aval lo lachalav*. They can go out if it's to dry the
udders, not if it's to catch the milk. What's the difference of
all these? So let's first read the גמרא *Gemara* as it continues.
ואיבעית אימא *Ve'iba'it eima*, הא והא רבי יהודה *ha ve'ha Rabbi Yehuda*.
The difference of can they go out or not go out is
רב יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, דתני *Detani*, it's both within רב יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda*. ולא קשיא *Velo kashya*: כאן ליבש כאן לחלב *kan leyabesh, kan
lachalav*. Difference whether you're trying to dry out the milk or trying
to catch the milk. תניא *Tanya*. We learned in the ברייתא *Beraisa*,
אמר רבי יהודה מעשה בעיזי בית אנטוכיא שהיו דדיהן גסים *amar rabbi
Yehuda ma'aseh be-izei beit antukhya she-hayu dadeihen gasim*. There was a story
with the goats of this place that they had very big udders,
ועשו להם כיסים *ve-asu la-hem kisim* and or that also the nipples
were large and they made for them these protectors כדי שלא ישרטו
דדיהם *kedei she-lo yisretu dadeihem* so they should not scrape on the
ground. Now let's talk for a minute about why these things matter.
If it's done to dry out, there's two reasons why that's good.
Number one, it makes means that they're tighter, so there's less of
a concern that they'll fall out. And it also somehow was seen
as for the sake of the animal. The animal's done nursing, so
then have it lactating is not healthy if they if the you
know or whatever not is painful if the animals aren't going to
be nursing from it. So it actually is done, it's sort of
like to help the animal to sort of dry out. Now, maybe
from the perspective of the owner who is taking away the small
to make them stop nursing, but anyway, that's tight and it's for
the sake of the animal. Catching the milk has two problems. It's
loose and also it's there not for the animal but to catch
the milk and therefore it's a type of a carrying. The final
example of scraping against the ground seems like that should always be
okay. That's what classic protector is. You do it to protect something
from being injured and that would seem that that is, you know,
that that is totally okay. So that seems to be some of
the issues around the goats. Okay, we will have to stop here.
We will, unfortunately, there's a great story coming up but we'll have
to wait for tomorrow.